A Guide to the Records of the Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs, 2013-2017
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs, 2013-2017
The Library of Virginia
52173
.70 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted records in this collection have been sealed but not removed from the collection. Types of sealed information may include, but are not limited to: medical and personal records.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 9 January 2018 from the Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs, State Capitol Building, 3rd Floor, Richmond, VA 23219.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 2010 Governor Robert F. McDonnell initiated legislative action which changed and re-organized the former Office of Commonwealth Preparedness (OCP) into the Office of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security (OVAHS). With this legislation the Department of Veterans Services (DVS) was moved from the Office of Public Safety to the Office of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security along with the Virginia War Memorial. In April of 2011 Terrie L. Suit was appointed by Governor McDonnell to the position of Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security after previously serving as Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness. James W. Hopper was appointed Deputy Secretary. She stepped down from the position on September 22nd, 2013 after being selected as the Chief Executive Office of the Virginia Association of REALTORS (VAR). Hopper, a previous staff member of McDonnell's tenure as Attorney General from 2006-2009 took over the Secretary's position until January 2013.
The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness had originated from Governor James Gilmore's Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel created after the September 11th terrorist attacks to better prevent and respond to such attacks in Virginia. Shortly thereafter, Governor-elect Mark R. Warner named John H. Hager to the newly created position of assistant to the governor for commonwealth preparedness, now a cabinet-level position, on 28 December 2001. Hager served as lieutenant governor under Governor James Gilmore and was a member of the Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel. On 31 January 2002, Governor Warner issued Executive Order 7, also known as the Secure Virginia Initiative, which rescinded Gilmore's Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel. Executive Order 7 also created the Secure Virginia Panel to review, evaluate, and make recommendations relating to emergency preparedness for the Commonwealth. The Secure Virginia Panel, which became the Secure Commonwealth Panel under Executive Order 69, was to consist of twenty members, later increased to twenty-eight members, under the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness as chairman. The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness and the Secure Commonwealth Panel were later codified under 2.2-304 through 2.2-306 of the Code of Virginia.
The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness was created with the purpose of developing a coordinated security and preparedness strategy and implementation plan. The Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness, who is appointed by the governor for a term of four years, is responsible for the general management of the Office. The Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security, was later renamed Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs by Governor Terry McAuliffe in 2013, with Homeland Security transferred to the Secretary of Public Safety, (renamed Secretary of Public Safety and Homeland Security).
Admiral John C. Harvey, Jr., served as Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs from 2013-2017. In 2017 Carlos Hopkins was appointed to serve as Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs.
Scope and Content
Records, 2013-2017, created and maintained by Secretary of Veterans and Defense Affairs, Admiral John C. Harvey, Jr. (2014-2017) and Carlos Hopkins (2017-present), during the administration of Governor Terry McAuliffe (2014-2018). The records include correspondence, memorandum, newsclippings, presentations, reports, studies, and other working papers.
Topics include payments from the Virginia Military Strategic Response Funds for improvements to localities and Forts; cyber security issues; environmental impacts statements; programs for veterans; Ft. Monroe Authority; Naval Station Norfolk Centennial celebration; constituent correspondence; grants relating to BRAC; and educational opportunities for military children.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Accomack County Public Schools, 2017. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Air Force Association, 2017. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Albemarle County: National Ground Intelligence Center, 2017. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Army National Guard Force Structure, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- City of Chesapeake Naval Auxiliary Landing Field, 2014-2017. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- College of William and Mary, Whole Government Center, 2016. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Constituent correspondence, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Constituent correspondence, 2016. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Constituent correspondence, 2017. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, General, 2014-2017. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Crater Planning District Commission (Petersburg, Va.), 2013-2014. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cyber Security Commission, 2014-2016. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Dept. of the Army (Ft. Belvoir, Va.), 2014-2015. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Dept. of the Army and Air Force, 2014-2017. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Dept. of Defense, Job training instruction, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Dept. of the Navy, 2014-2017. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Development of Virginia Veterans Transition Portal, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Fairfax County Veterans Treatment Docket, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Federal funding for Veterans Care Centers, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Ft. Monroe, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Ft. Monroe, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Ft. Monroe, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Ft. Monroe, 2017. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- George Mason University, Economic Adjustment Grant, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- George Mason University, Office of Military Services, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- George Mason University, Veterans Entrepreneurship Initiatives, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- City of Hampton, Encroachment Grant, 2017. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- James City County, Redesignating lot adjacent to Ft. Eustis, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Military Medics and Corpsmen Program, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- The Muster DC, 2017. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Norfolk International Airport, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- State Military Reservation Camp Pendleton (Va.), 2014-2017. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Virginia Beach, Grant, 2014-2016. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Virginia Board of Workforce Development, 2017. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Virginia Compact on National Service, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Virginia Council on the Interstate Compact, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 17)